Benjamin B. Daniels

benjamin.daniels@georgetown.edu

benjaminbdaniels.com github.com/bbdaniels +1 (203) 687-9943

PROFILE

Development researcher with 8 years of international field and data experience

Extensive published research specializing in the quality of primary health care and public health Statistical programming expertise, including developing best practices and tools for reproducible research Experience planning and managing fieldwork in collaboration with local clients and partners Created trainings, interactive sessions, manuals, blog posts, and other teaching resources Supervised research assistants, consultants, interns, and contractors on data collection, coding, and analysis

EDUCATION

MSc Economics and Philosophy (with Merit)

London School of Economics and Social Science

BA Economics Claremont, CA, 2011

Pomona College

WORK EXPERIENCE

Georgetown University 2019 – Present

Research Fellow, Georgetown University Initiative on Innovation, Development and Evaluation (gui²de)

- · Provided support for a portfolio of research studies on primary health care quality and public health
- · Developed and delivered training program for onboarding and management of student research assistants

The World Bank — Development Economics Vice Presidency (DEC) Washington, DC, and international

2011 – Present

London, UK, 2013

Data Coordinator, Development Impact Evaluations Department (DIME Analytics)

2017 - Present

- Ensured research quality for all 20+ DIME economists for data collection, analysis, and publication
- · Developed and disseminated best practices for reproducible research through the DIME Wiki,
- · Contributed to World Bank GitHub, continuing education, pre-publication code review, and training
- · Authored Stata code packages for standardizing data collection and analysis processes
- · Supported data collection on all projects, including sampling and randomization and SurveyCTO Enterprise
- · Supported hiring process including technical interviews, Stata evaluations, and onboarding and training

Researcher, Quality of Tuberculosis Care in Urban India (QuTUB)

2014 - 2019

- · Managed data collection and statistical analysis for a \$1.3M study on tuberculosis (TB) care in urban India
- · Supported design and implementation of RCT evaluation of TB care programs in Mumbai and Patna,
- · Handled on-site coordination and data sharing with local implementing NGOs
- · Developed survey instruments and liaised with vendor for real-time digital data entry system
- · Managed data collection process over 10 survey rounds totaling 10,000 standardized patient (SP) interactions
- · Led analysis of first major field use of SPs for TB and antibiotic use and misuse in Indian pharmacies
- · Analyzed NGO programmatic data on 200,000 real patients to assess patterns of provider behavior change

Researcher, Kenya Patient Safety Impact Evaluation (KePSIE)

2013 - 2014

- · Led preliminary analysis of all 10,000 registered health facilities for the Kenyan government
- · Designed and field-tested electronic data collection at 42 Nairobi facilities for a \$1M evaluation
- · Pilot work led to first-authored publication comparing primary care quality in India, China, and Kenya

PUBLICATIONS

- "Use of standardised patients for healthcare quality research in low-and middle-income countries." *BMJ Global Health* 4.5 (2019): e001669. With Kwan, Ada, et al.
- "How to do (or not to do) ... using the standardized patient method to measure clinical quality of care in LMIC health facilities." *Health Policy and Planning* 2019 Aug. With King J, et al.
- "Lessons on the quality of tuberculosis diagnosis from standardized patients in China, India, Kenya, and South Africa." *Journal of Clinical Tuberculosis and Other Mycobacterial Diseases* 2019 Jun 7:100109. With Kwan A., Pai M., and Das J. (first author)
- "Use of standardised patients to assess gender differences in quality of tuberculosis care in urban India: a two-city, cross-sectional study" *Lancet Global Health* (2019) 7:e633-e643. With Kwan, A., et al. (joint first author)
- "Variations in the quality of tuberculosis care in urban India: A cross-sectional, standardized patient study in two cities." *PLoS medicine* (2018) 15.9:e1002653. With Kwan, A., et al. (joint first author)
- "Use of standardised patients to assess quality of healthcare in Nairobi, Kenya: a pilot, cross-sectional study with international comparisons." *BMJ Global Health* (2017) 2:e000333. With Dolinger, A., et al. (first author)
- "Social equity issues in the distribution of feed-in tariff policy benefits: a cross sectional analysis from England and Wales using spatial census and policy data." *Energy Policy* (2017) 106:255-65. With Grover, D.
- "Use of standardised patients to assess antibiotic dispensing for tuberculosis by pharmacies in urban India: a cross-sectional study." *Lancet Infectious Diseases* (2016) 15:30215-8. With Satyanarayana, S., et al.
- "Examining the quality of medicines at Kenyan healthcare facilities: a validation of an alternate post-market surveillance model that uses standardized patients."

 *Drugs Real World Outcomes (2016) 1-11. With Wafula, F., et al.
- "Quality and Equity in Basic Health Care Services in Vietnam: Findings from the 2015 Vietnam District and Commune Health Facility Survey." World Bank Report No. AUS13083. (2016) With Demombynes, G., et al.
- "Use of standardised patients to assess quality of tuberculosis care: a pilot, cross-sectional study." *Lancet Infectious Diseases* (2015) 15:1305-13. With Das, J., et al.

MISCELLANEOUS

Book: Data for Development Impact

worldbank.github.com/d4di

Stata commands for various research tasks

github.com/bbdaniels/stata

iefieldkit: commands for data collection and cleaning

github.com/worldbank/iefieldkit

ietoolkit: commands for impact evaluation data analysis

github.com/worldbank/ietoolkit

Research, Data Management, and Analysis

Stata (Advanced); SurveyCTO (Advanced); GitHub (Advanced)

GitKraken Ambassador; Berkeley Initiative for Transparency in the Social Sciences Catalyst

World Bank Strategic Impact Evaluation Fund

Won \$150,000 SIEF grant for "Generating Reform in the Primary Healthcare System of Estonia" Created partnership with World Bank project team and Estonian Health Insurance Fund Developed project to scale up impact evaluation using national health insurance claims data

REFERENCES AVAILABLE UPON REQUEST